Hello, I'm your host David Bernard and
my guest today is Thomas Bati, an
independent consultant focused on
subscription app growth. Over the past
decade, Thomas has worked with hundreds
of clients and helped manage nine digits
in ad spend with a positive return. On
the podcast, I talk with Thomas about
using signal engineering to optimize ad
spend, how AI is changing creative
testing, and why most people should
avoid appto for now. Hey Thomas, thanks
so much for joining me on the podcast
again.
>> Hi David, always happy to come back.
There's one of one of this time of the
year. I look forward chatting to you and
browsing some new topics around apps. So
yeah, happy to be here. Yeah, I think
we're we're going to kind of make this
an annual thing. We just the last three
years in a row, I think we've done it in
the in the late summer, early fall. So,
uh we'll just make this a every every
summer kind of thing.
>> All right, that's the date.
>> So, the main thing I wanted to talk to
you about today was signal engineering.
We've done a webinar on it. You've
talked about it quite a bit. People have
been blogging about it. But before we
get there, there are a few kind of like
hot topics that I thought people would
really enjoy hearing from you about. And
so let's do those first and then we'll
dig into signal engineering. And you
know, maybe this is going to be a two or
three hour podcast. Let's uh see how it
goes.
So one of the things I wanted to talk to
you about is AI and AI creative
generation. And you know, there's been a
lot of noise lately about, you know, oh,
Facebook's just going to or Meta is just
going to, you know, take all your assets
and figure everything out and just, you
know, 100% automate all your ads at some
point in the next like 18 months. Like,
it's it's going to generate humanl
looking people. It's going to write your
taglines for you. It's going to just do
everything. It's going to customize it
to every individual. and it's just going
to be this like utopia of ads. And
that's that's the take I've been hearing
from a lot of folks. But I saw a tweet
from you recently with a a bit of a
contrarian spin on that. And so I'd love
to hear how you think about using AI in
creative generation in just in the
entire ad creation process and kind of
what to watch out for and where you
think things are headed. There's a lot
of focus on using AI specifically for
this like for producing creatives and I
think that's actually a mistake in the
sense of it's hiding the fact that we
can use AI for a number of other things
that are not creative production. Of
course, it's a natural because because
of the cost of production but also like
of ideation as well and how we can make
multiple variants much easier than
before. So it's a little bit of it's so
obvious that 95% of the discussion is
there. But my first answer would be
maybe we haven't done that much
elsewhere and I think especially in
creative analysis is is where there's a
bit of a gap. I'm seeing a couple of
tools coming up and some people but it's
still a rare conversation like a lot of
the focus is on creative production and
that's kind of expected in a way. I
think if we if we look back since GPT
came out like early on obviously was
like mostly text and then we got like
midjourney and Delhi but like static
pictures at least for apps is is a
relatively small amount of of the ads
that are actually thrown out there and
text are important especially on Google
and elsewhere but like for paid social
for meta for Tik Tok and for the gaming
networks like text is is a very small to
significant part so so obviously the
acceleration has mostly been around the
last 6 12 months which is where video
creation became really possible. I mean
until a year ago we're in summer 25
until last summer the quality of AI
production for video was not good enough
for ad creation and then as everything
AI it sort of accelerated so massively
that I don't think I know a single team
who's not using any AI tool for ad
production which doesn't mean that 100%
of ads are ad generated are AI generated
yet and I don't think we'll ever reach
100% unless one platform decide that
there's no other choice but I don't
think it's going to be it Like I think
it's going to be a bit of a mix and
probably it's going to be the majority
but it doesn't mean it's going to be the
entirety especially around creation like
I mean you can use it not just to
generate the picture itself but also to
generate like the briefings and I mean
multiple varants is another use. So
within creative production there's like
many layers of how you use AI. It's not
like so it could be to create variance,
could be to find new ideas and then
sometimes you'd use several tools in a
row like one to generate ideas and one
to classify them and try them and then
later one to produce them. There's
there's one that's very exciting. I I
saw I saw the message last week and I
thought, "Oh, crazy." I I remember
writing something about it six years
ago, so pre GPT. So it was kind of funny
which was like oh it's the first time
ever there's a tool that enables you to
actually test a creative without
spending a single dollar and there's
basically this pool of artificial humans
that are used they're not humans they're
just AI generated to classify if an ad
has a chance to become a winner without
to spend any money which is which is the
dream because I mean on one side we need
to produce a lot of stuff to find out
what works and the starts out there are
like roughly you have to produce 50
creative to have one that is actually a
winner and this winner is going to take
90 plus% of the ad spend. That's kind of
a normal winner takes all mechanics that
happens in ads. So obviously create
because we you need 50 to to find one
and sometimes more teams accelerating of
creating a hundred a week thousands
every month to to find a couple of
winners like and so that's the that's an
obvious use but uh having like something
that tells you without having to do
creative testing which one has the most
chance to win is something that is still
very nent very pioneer and I don't think
it's going to fully replace proper
creative testing where you put a little
bit of money behind it But it's
definitely one way I'm looking forward
about acceleration in the next year.
Like we're not there yet, but it's
something I can see it's coming in
analysis as well. I think it's going to
accelerate especially around patterns
like which hooks have always worked and
which not then you can come up and it's
it's sort of all entangle into
accelerating because of these different
layers. One accelerates the next one and
amplify let's say the next one. It's all
very exciting as of Meta making and Mark
Zuckerberg in particular making
declaration that his goal is that
there's no more assets at all that it's
all generated. I think was voluntarily
provocative about the direction it's
taking. I don't think we're going to get
there in the next one to three years and
certainly not 18 months but it's
certainly the direction it's taking. I
mean Google has done a lot of it early
on with UIC and is still doing a lot of
it. Meta has done some of it and is
clearly now accelerating and I can see
why this declaration I mean Zuk said it
in a way to prepare people that it's
coming not necessarily that this is the
ultimate form that they talk about is
what's going to be there in 18 months
but it's pretty logical like in terms of
personalizing
parts of the creative like you could
find for example a script of a creative
like something that fairly resonates
with a lot of your audience but then if
you magnify that the text can be
customized, that the character in the in
the ad can be customized and somebody
would add something somebody looking
more like them or a little bit older and
then you can cater to even more
audience. That makes a lot of sense.
Like I'm seeing this happening today in
a half manual way, which is like, oh,
I've got something that wins. Let's
produce 50 of them and one with an older
guy and one with a black woman and one
with a 20 years old and one with a
whatever. And you just try them. No, but
I I can see how right now it's more like
a marketer's idea of, oh, I've got
something that wins. Let's make variance
out of it into the platform automating
more of this. And
>> so in the in the grand scheme of things,
does make sense that we take that
direction? I don't think it's going to
be ultimately the the only way the
creatives are produced either.
>> Where do you see folks failing with this
right now? Or what do you think that
things to watch out for? I mean, you
kind of alluded to it that these tools
that kind of pick the winners ahead of
time maybe shouldn't be relied on 100%,
but what other things are you seeing
that you think teams are doing or, you
know, customers that clients that you
work with have suggested that you're
like, I don't think we're quite like
that's not the right direction yet.
>> It's hard to pinpoint one in particular.
Well, one thing that is always a tricky
balance, a tricky tra tradeoff is when
you find winners, obviously they're
they're so much better than the rest
that you want to double down on this.
So, you create a lot of variance of it.
And ultimately, sometimes I look at some
accounts and I'm like, okay, but all
you've got there is one concept. Like,
yeah, you've got a few ads, but it's
more of the same. And sooner or later,
this is going to go down and and you
have to prepare a lot more. So it's kind
of like
instead of exploring so many more
concept and and the majority will fail
like the trick between how much do I
have doubled on winners but how much do
I prepare what's next doing something
that has more likelihood to fail in the
short term but more likelihood to be
required in the long term is is very
hard to balance like and obviously
everybody's short-term looking
especially in UAE you know we look at
the results from yesterday and last
quarter already doesn't exist anymore So
yeah, long-term preparation of what next
and audience expansion especially when
you spend at scale like if the account
is relatively small. I mean you can tap
on the same concept over and over and
with a few variants you can push it
around months but everything is
accelerating even in ads and I think
this is especially visible in in Tik Tok
where the trends go so much faster like
around music around the specific hooks
around the first seconds around even
concept of ads like that really
accelerating and so you can't just
double down on stuff like it just got to
create I think like AI obviously enable
us to go faster in like, oh, this works.
I'm going to produce 100 version of it.
And even if in two weeks this concept is
dead, I'm going to have used it in the
meantime. So, even more useful for cases
like on Tik Tok where fatigue is much
faster than for example on YouTube where
you probably still want to craft a lot
more less ads but go deeper. The other
one because the question was where do
you sit failing? And here there's
something that I don't want to accept,
but I still have to, which is we don't
understand why winning ads win. And so
we have this tendency. Eric Sford is the
extremist about it about don't even try
to understand why it works. It's just a
waste of time. I'm not that far, but in
a way, yeah, I've seen teams fail a lot
on I don't know, you'd use an AI tool
and say, "Oh, look, those are my 200
last creatives. Those three are the
best. everything else fails. Tell me
why. And here it's sort of like you will
get a result and you will get some
patterns but I don't think those
patterns push you to the next one where
you can actually replicate it so easily
like the very specific details of
psychology how people react. The kind of
audience that is there is really hard to
explain. So I'm still doing it and I
still understand why people would do it
because then for iteration it brings you
to the next one. You want to learn from
what you've done to keep progressing and
it and it's natural and sometimes maybe
it helps but honestly it's a little bit
of overstated in the it's very hard to
understand why winning ads win and our
human criteria is not very good but
actually the LLMs they're not very good
either like they could spot a couple
patterns and all
>> but it's not going to make the next
winning ad that much easier either. It's
sad, but in a way it's more like, okay,
let's massproduce and see what sticks
rather than let's try to really explain
why it works. And even ads from
competitors, you you'd be like trying to
understand why they were and whether
you're doing it with a team and
brainstorm or you're using doing it
through AI or probably the best of is
doing both still the outcome is slim and
pretty bad.
>> Well, the next question I want to ask is
what tools are you currently seeing
success with? But that'll turn this into
like a 5-hour podcast. And so I was
thinking as you were responding to that
last question that we we should just do
a webinar like you maybe Nathan Hudson,
maybe Marcus Burke, get a few people who
are really into this and do a whole
webinar specifically on like what tools
are working. I think that's going to be
changing so quickly that maybe doing it
on podcast isn't as good as just doing a
webinar and some blog posts that we can
update over time. But the next big topic
I wanted to bring up was app to web, the
Epic lawsuit, the injunction. If you're
listening to this podcast, surely you
know, so we're not going to go over it
all, but what are you seeing apps do
currently? And are you seeing things
work in sending people from the app to
the web? And then as as a precursor, you
probably you've been on vacation, so you
probably hadn't had a chance to listen,
but the podcast episode just prior to
this one, I talked to Zumba and they are
seeing success sending people to the web
and they've been doing a lot of
experimentation. And then as I've shared
on other episodes, I'm also hearing from
a ton of folks that they're scared to do
it because they don't want Apple to stop
featuring them. They don't want to get
in a bad position with Apple. Um, and so
there seems to be like a lot of variance
going on right now with whether you
should even try sending people out of
the app to the web, who you should send
out of the app to the web, what
experiments you should do. So, you know,
give us a a quick take on, you know,
August 2025, where are things at with
app to web and where do you see things
going?
>> Sure. If I were to like super simplify
like if you got like a big brand or if
you've got like some something that
people already wants from the get-go,
it's much more likely than app to web is
going to work. So if you Spotify, it's
obvious if even Zumba, but I think the
app is pretty recent, but it's the
official app of Zumba and like people
already know what it is. Like there is a
trust factor in there. If you're an
indie developer and you're launching a
brandless app last month, it's very
likely that app to web is a full zeran
in the sense that one, you can't do it
all because you've got a small team or
it's just you. Two, it's less likely to
work because you don't have like this
recognition, this brand and people are
less likely to like go and three the
analysis is actually quite tricky. So
you need you need minimum resources to
execute this minimum resources not just
in designing a great flow which is like
a requirement because a poor flow will
will make it not work where it could
have but actually analyzing properly and
comparing the the two is not as easy as
it looks like refund works different
renewal works different free trial works
very different you need to deal with
like the amount of small detail and and
one thing that is really interesting
from the folks for whom it does work to
send people outside of the app is that
typically they don't sell the same plans
like what work on an app to web flow is
much closer to what you see in a web to
app flow like where the first touch
point is on the web and then you charge
and then only they go to the app than
what you see through APS like and so if
you port the exact same flow and your
analysis level is not deep enough to
understand all the small details that
are going to change you could actually
be misfiring and believe you're doing
something great when it's not or vice
versa now or actually missing out on a
it's not as easy as it looks. So my big
advice is that if you're big and you
have the resource and you've got the
brand, sure, go try it like right now.
If you're very small and it's just you,
don't even try. It's not worth it.
You're only paying 50% and the
complexity, you're probably better off
investing your efforts elsewhere. But
obviously the majority of people will
land somewhere in between. And it's at
which time do we make the choice to
actually experiment with this. And
curiously
the the teams I worked the closest with
they decided not to even test. Like I
was like why? I was like because
prioritization is saying no to great
ideas. No saying no to stupid ideas. And
we can't do it all. And we've got the
this road map for the next three six
months where we've got like very big
projects going on. we're going to wait
for the dust to settle because then
there was the other appeal and then we
didn't know how Apple would react like I
mean now I think the dust starts to
settle and we see more or less other
examples and
Apple might change things later but for
now they haven't taken like massive
retaliation stuff sometimes there's a
first mover advantage like and for
example the ones who were advertising on
Tik Tok early obviously they like it was
a huge advantage I'd rather have people
from teams that experiment a not do it
and then listen to what they do and
shortcut to what they think is working
rather because there's a lot to test
there like I mean the different flaws
the pricing the how do you charge how do
you prioritize the Apple payment versus
not and so on like it's like there's a
lot of factors so the the the teams I'm
working with they're like yeah we're
looking at it we're talking to people
about it but we're going to push it into
the next step of the road map where we
think we can execute faster then and we
also have a little more guarantee about
Apple wants or doesn't want. So I had a
couple of folks testing and actually in
one case it's not a big app and it does
make a difference for them. So maybe
even against my own advice, they went
for it and it does work for them. But
they just crossed the small business
program. So now they're paying 30%. So
for them obviously was a little bit of a
below 1 million. I mean when you're
paying already 15% I don't think like
anybody should really try it un unless
you're very web based from the beginning
like you had a business on the web and
you already have a lot of tooling and a
lot of experience and you can go but
otherwise yeah I mean it's for later
phases all in all it's great that there
is the option like I'm very happy that
we can do more some people are going to
go IP only some people are going to go
web payment only and the most
sophisticated folks will be able to
determine which user which flow flow
which moment which price is going to
work which obviously requires a lot more
work and is not as easy as it looks. I
think the only lie here is to tell
people that oh it's easy send your
people over there and you save 30% of
fee which is like a complete lie but uh
all the rest I'm happy the option exists
and I'm happy to see different for and
and I've seen experiments in both sides
so it was really curious and trying to
understand like why did it work in this
field and not in that field even
regardless of the brand power that you
have like the brand awareness the
vertical also plays a big role like In
some verticals I where the the purchase
is a lot more instinctive and where
yeah the AP is great in this case though
there are verticals and verticals
there's brand and brands there's your
yeah I think it's great to have the
options uh but uh yeah not probably for
indies it's a bad idea and and for
Spotify it's the best news ever.
>> Yeah.
Yeah. No, I think that's a a great
summary and a good kind of take for
folks right now. If you have the
resources, you have the team, and I
thought that point was really great that
>> if you're going to do it, you can't
really halfass it. You really need to
think about it as a as an initiative
that like we're going to
>> send people to the web, but then we're
going to iterate on that flow. We're
going to experiment. We're going to add
steps. We're going to remove steps. and
and that was the conversation with Zumba
that that we had. So, you know, for
folks listening to the podcast who
hadn't listened to that episode, if
you're curious uh to get a deep dive,
you know, they really put a lot of
resources in it. And to Thomas's point,
you know, they've been selling on the
web for decades. You know, they started
20 something 24 years ago selling VHS
tapes uh on infomercials. So they
already had all the infrastructure, they
had the teams, they had everything and
and they had the ability as a team to
dedicate those resources and and then
you know they did a lot of testing and
like one of the things that worked for
them was actually doing package
selection inside the app and only
sending to the web just for the payment
piece. So the person had already kind of
like selected the package, kind of made
a commitment and then the web part is
only payment. it's only checkout and
it's defaulted to Apple Pay and that's
where they saw like the the big win
start to happen. So if if you are going
to try that's probably one of the first
experiments to do is to do package
selection in the app and then make the
web just the check out and then make
that as like quick seamless least
confusing no options like you just pay
and then get back to the app. But I
think that that was a great summary. So
I appreciate your thoughts there. The
last thing before we get to signal
engineering is hybrid monetization. I
mean, this is something we've been
talking about for years, but I feel like
it's still for for non-game apps and
then for, you know, there there's
certain categories where hybrid
monetization has worked and has, you
know, there are some kind of best
practices starting to be established,
but I feel like it it's going to be one
of those trends that's going to continue
to accelerate. And AI is a good example.
And to be honest, I'm so frustrated with
Claude. I use Claude a ton in my
day-to-day work now, mostly just like a
brainstorming partner and like get
summaries of podcasts I listen to and
things like that. And lately, I've been
hitting their usage limits and there's
no that I don't get just a freaking
button like like give me give me 20 more
usages for five bucks or whatever. like
those kind of things in especially for
AI apps or where there where you are
resource constrained having some kind of
way to get past the those limitations I
think is just an obvious thing for a lot
of these companies to start doing but I
think there's so many other applications
so what are you seeing work and where do
you see things continuing to go with
figuring out hybrid monetization in apps
I agree it's been it's been pretty slow
I I've been advocating for not doing
only subscription for quite a while and
most most the apps I work with they're
like it's only subscription and that's
it and and and I could see and I could
see a few success here and there for
very different cases some with ads for
the people who don't subscribe but when
you retain a lot of subscription apps
they just don't retain the free court at
all their their fake premium is you pay
or you're going to churn anyway so
obviously they're for specific cases AP
mostly for upselles and so on and then a
lot of ecoms and affiliates head sales
and so on, which makes sense for very
specific cases as well, but not for
everybody. So, I think like you have to
pick up the the model, but overall I'm
I'm looking back at the last two years
and I'm a little bit surprised that it's
been so slow and I think one of the
reason has been the complexity around
it. Like same same as the app to web
stuff. It's it can't really be done
easily. like there's no obvious way of
oh I'm going to put ads in the app and
it's going to increase my conversion or
I'm going to put on top of the
subscription and no it's really tricky
and I think that's the reason it's been
so slow and actually all the apps that
are have some kind of AI usage are
finally accelerating this trend because
they've got no other choice and it's
true that the big models like cloud and
chip and so on
>> they mostly decided to go for tiered
subscription so I I don't know, JGBD,
you pay $20 a month and uh if you didn't
have any, well, you stop paying $200 a
month or whatever. But for a lot of apps
that are like usage based, this is a
model, but actually the AIP makes a lot
of sense where you can buy credits on
top. I'm working on a project right now
where they have both T subscription and
credits on top so that no user face the
frustration that you just had that maybe
you didn't want to fully upgrade to the
super pro package but then for one use
case you're working on something today
and you would just have added five or 10
bucks of credits and and finish it and
they've got a very smart team of several
people that have been thinking through
it for months and it's really hard to
design well like to avoid
cannibalization to not frustrate users
to make something that is fair in term
of pricing for users but also for the
developer like it's very tricky so I
think it's mostly down to this
complexity that it's been fairly small
that it's a natural case for AI just
because there's cost so obviously you
need to to find a way that you don't
lose money but the rest has been slow
because of complexity but also because
it's sort of the last person of grind
that you get like there's so any
lowerhanging fruit around your
subscription and I'm glad today there is
a normal conversation to talk about
pricing and pay wall design and how you
package and the free trial and this and
that and 3 four years ago this was like
still a little bit niche and it
surprised me how people didn't realize
that they could like increase their
revenue massively by iterating a lot
because there's been such such an
acceleration there and the the overall
level has gone up so fast I think
eventually it's still going to come that
hybrid situation is going to is going to
come just taking a very long time
because of complexity and for many
people that's okay you should nobody
should jump into it I think just at some
point I've seen how the the improvement
curve of of those experiment on pricing
is slowing down that's probably an
indicator of maybe maybe it's time to
try something different but if you're
still making big wins on pricing and
packaging just with subscription keep
going at it until it slows down
>> and and funny enough I als also use chat
GPT quite a bit, but I'm on the pro plan
with chat GPT because I use deep
research so much in chat GPT and so I
probably so chat GPT I actually pay for
out of my personal business because I
use it so much more for like personal
stuff and for like my side project
business even though I actually do use
it a ton for like revenue cat work but
then claude is actually built through
revenue cat as a like employee expense
and so I probably should just ask for
the higher tier and that's kind of what
they're counting done. So you're to your
point, if you're not already in a tiered
subscription uh model, that's the first
step before going to to hybrid. But one
of the places I I do think and I've
heard this from Tammy Taw at Google. You
know, she spoke last year at App Growth
Annual. She did a podcast mini episode
for the state of subscription apps
report. And one of the things Google has
been pushing really heavily because they
see the numbers and they see it
succeeding so well is working on hybrid
monetization outside the US. And so
maybe that's another kind of angle where
if things are going really well in the
US and you're still have lowhanging
fruit there, but you have the bandwidth,
then experimenting with hybrid
monetization outside the US, maybe what
it takes to start seeing more wins
outside the US of offering people
non-recurring purchases, non-recurring
subscriptions, offering these one-time
purchases that make it a little easier
to to bite off, especially in the
countries where subscriptions aren't as
widely accepted and and used. So that'd
be another kind of vector to think about
if whether or not you should be
experimenting with hybrid monetization.
It made me think differently about it
and once you hear it, yeah, it's pretty
natural where that where where there's a
very high not purchase power but like
sort of habit of paying apps obviously
the reward is probably further away but
then on Android where it's a little bit
harder to convert and outside of the US
and when you combine the two of it is
much harder like obviously the
conversion rate on Android international
versus US iOS are extremely different.
does make sense to start there. But then
it joins my point that it increased
complexity in the sense of okay so on US
iOS I need to do the tier subscription
and then for Latin America I need to add
this like payment options because there
it's what works because they've got less
credit cards especially in Brazil
Argentina for example where credit cards
international credit cards are a bit
limited and then for another region it's
going to be something else that's going
to work. So obviously if you're a big
company and you can dedicate you can
zoom on an area and find out what works
for them that's great but I have a lot
of apps I work with that operates in 200
countries and even though there is uh
uplift to be found the amount of effort
that needs to be deployed to find all
these individual uplift left and right
is a huge work so it really depends the
type of organization you're in and the
focus you're on. I I know a lot of
smaller folks are like, "Yeah, I operate
everywhere, but 95% of my effort is
going to the US." I understand why for
them hybrid monetization is like
something that's on the road map for
2031 or something.
>> Yeah. No, it makes a ton of sense. Funny
enough, I mean, all three topics we've
we've had so far are around
prioritization is that, you know,
they're all good ideas, but you need to
make sure you've got the resources in
place and the can put in the effort to
actually make it work because it's not
just going to be this automatic big win.
And I mean, that may be another key too
is like if your core product isn't
working in the US,
like you need to make it work first.
like it's not this magic unlock unless
for some reason you know the app has
taken off in some other country or
there's a use case outside the US it
makes a ton of sense but other than that
it's not some magic unlock that if it's
not working in the US if you're not able
to charge subscription on iOS and people
aren't willing to pay that it's some
magic unlock that you're going to do
this outside the US and see all this
success so it's like you got to have
that core product the value the
activation the onboarding flows and
everything else pretty well dialed in
and it should be working hopefully in
the US before you even think about
trying this around the world.
>> It's very hard to pioneer anything
really. It doesn't mean we shouldn't try
but like these models sometimes it's
natural like you look at dating for
example is is a vertical where there was
always a lot more hybrid monetization
than elsewhere because there were ads
and there were specific IABS and so on
and probably if you're in this vertical
you should try earlier than others
because there's a lot of success that
has been found and users are more used
to it
>> and you can follow the patterns that
have already been established
>> exactly you can follow some patterns
like if nobody's doing it in your
vertical there might be a reason that if
you're the first one, I mean, you you
could create something new and find
success, but it's going to cost so much
more to find out that Yeah. Sometimes
just not natural.
>> Yeah. All right. Well, let's jump into
signal engineering next. So, you emailed
me in the spring and you were like,
"Hey, David, I've been toying with this
concept and I don't even remember if you
named it in that first email or if you
came up with a name later, but I feel
like I'm hearing the term signal
engineering all over the place now." But
I guess take me back to what is signal
engineering and then I mean I know
people have been doing versions of this
for a long time, but like what what's
the origin of of you in the spring
thinking that this was kind of the next
hot topic or the next place that that
user acquisition team should be putting
some effort into. So what we're talking
about here is the optimization of what
what we call the signal is the data we
send back to a non network to an
advertising platform to optimize the ads
from. So when you tell Facebook, oh I
want installs, they're going to send
installs, but then it's probably not
going to get you very far. And beyond
the install, it can be many things. So
some people optimize for free trials,
optim some people optimize for day one
retention or whatever. And this has been
very much always existed but in my
opinion underlooked. And so it's it's
nothing new but I kind of felt that the
discussion over the last couple of years
was 90% creative. And it's obvious that
the creative is by far one of the
biggest lover if not the biggest lover
in what's going to make ad spend or paid
media work or not. But then doesn't mean
is the only one. And I was like, so my
intention here was like I want to remind
people that there are several factors at
play and that if you're sending terrible
data back to Facebook and Google, you
can be great at creative, you're still
going to have a problem. And the other
realization was let's say there's three
position of serial engineering. One is
the data you're sending back is
completely messed up. And that's
actually a quite frequent case in small
and in bigger organization. And
honestly, if that's the case, you're
probably better off fixing it before
iterating on anything else. Like if if
there's something wrong with the signals
that you're sending back, it's your top
priority to at least fix it, understand
what you're passing. You don't have to
get super sophisticated, but at least
you need to be sure of what you're
sending back and having a quality of
event that is passing correctly and so
on. It's like it's a must have like it's
not like ah nice to experiment all no if
it's broken you got to fix it and then
there's the majority of cases of people
who don't have broken data but haven't
thought much through it like okay let's
optimize through the free trials and
we'll see or or have something set up I
I have one particular case where they
actually find and it's somewhat not
super sophisticated but like a little
bit more elaborate scheme where they
were sending back different signals when
people were taking different types of
subscriptions. So like they have a mixed
up of of user type and weekly yearly and
they just have a multiplier say okay if
it's the weekly subscription from a
normal user send one and if it's a
yearly subscription from a business user
send X5 back to the platform. So, but
then they hardcoded it and they iterated
for a year and a half on the pricing and
so on. And when I came in, I realized
that this hard coding that did make a
lot of sense back when they did it was
actually not representative of the value
of users that were coming in. And then
it became again a priority to fix in the
sense of to to get closer to the real
value. So, and and the last phase is
when you get really sophisticated. So I
went a little bit around but like if
it's broken you really need to fix it
find a place where you're comfortable
with and dedicate your attention on
creative and declassifying and other
things but at some point as you grow
becoming a little bit more sophisticated
about it and having sending something
better than just all your free trials
combined is probably can unlock value at
a different and and most people look to
unlock value everywhere. So I it doesn't
mean here you need to be super big and
have a super big brand to do it. I've
spoken to a few people and I have one
case that will be on the revenue cap
blog at some point when I finish to wrap
up where a fairly young app has found
tremendous uplift by changing the events
they were sending and they were working
in parallel on creative but then it
accelerated what they could do uh in a
way. So three state broken normal and
sophisticated.
>> Yeah. Well, and and that's what I I I
wanted to step back to the to the broken
part because I don't know and may maybe
this is just my vantage point inside
Revenue Cat because we end up talking to
so many apps where their data is just
completely broken. So my estimate is
much higher just because that's who we
talk to I guess more. Tell me a little
bit more because I'm sure there's going
to be people on the podcast listening to
the podcast where they're going to hear
you say that and think, "Ah, I I don't
feel like I can trust my data." So, so
what do you mean by that? And then like
where do you see data being broken in
ways and you kind of already shared
shared one but what are the steps or
what are the tools or what are the the
kind of basics that you should have in
place for for even monitoring to make
sure that things don't break even when
you think they're working. How do you
figure out whether your data is good or
not?
So, it's always hard to prevent future
breaks, but uh I know when somebody
tells me like, "Hey, go go go check my
ad account. Tell me what you think or
make a note." I don't make so many of
them, but like sometimes, maybe it's a
friend, maybe it's a portfolio company,
so I still do it. And they say, "Oh,
here here's the ad manager." And I say,
"I don't care about the ads manager.
Show me the events manager." Like, so
Facebook call it events manager. In
Google, it's called goals. That's the
first place I look. I don't even look at
the ad account. And the first thing I'm
going to check is does the amount of
conversion which whatever this
conversion is. So let's say it's going
to be install and free trial and paid
subscriptions to simplify. And I'm going
to go check in the event manager. Do the
number that the platform reports being
sent match more or less what we have
internally and very often it's not the
case. I really don't care about a 5%
discrepancy here and it's never going to
100% match and that's okay. And there's
number of answer of why it's not 100%.
It doesn't matter. But in so many cases,
I'm seeing 30% or 50%. And this this is
going to be a major problem that I need
to fix before seeing anything else. So I
take Facebook as an example because it's
a big example, but I'm going to go to
the events manager and I'm going to say,
okay, show me last 30 days or last seven
days. How many install did you see? How
many free trial did you see in total
without attribution? Not the ones that
Facebook thinks.
not the one that Google attributes to
this particular paid activity but like
what we're actually sending them because
they reported there and I'm going to
compare it with something like count or
amplitude or mix panel or whatever they
have that is internal before we send it.
If I'm seeing more than 10% discrepancy
here it's going to be a problem. Those
tools they're not particularly
sophisticated but they're not
particularly easy to understand either.
So it's sometimes kind of tricky to
match the dates, the geographies, the
platform properly and so to debug that
actually the data I'm seeing there is
the one that is supposed to be there. I
remember making mistakes myself
sometimes like I don't know one case I
was like why am I seeing double the
event on Facebook? How is this even
possible that there's twice as many
users that we actually have? It's just
that there are two sources that Meta
managed to the duplicate but that
doesn't show up like this in the event
manager. So the first step I do is what
the platform is receiving is it matching
more or less what we think is happening
because if that's not the case well
after that they're going to try
attributing to a campaign and there
there's a whole lot of other things that
can happen. One that you don't trust
attribution which I would understand but
one that among those signals that you
sent maybe some didn't have the right
parameters. Maybe I don't know I
remember making a change and and yeah
we're like oh only 20% of the conversion
are passing like 100% is passing to the
event manager but only 20% of what we
think is happening is being reported at
the others and actually meta couldn't
attribute it on AM and it was only
reporting the double opting like the
IDFA people until we fixed it and so
yeah the the step one is is the total
actually matching uh because and I'm
saying it because if it's not nothing
else can
And it's kind of an easy check to do.
Like there can be many other problem.
It's just one. But that that it's it's
so common and it's so blocking of doing
anything that that's always the first
thing I'm I'm checking. What drives nuts
is that when it doesn't work, the amount
of reason that can be for it not to
work. But that's something you need to
fix yes or yes like uh one way or
another. That could be changing the
source. That could be sending different
parameters to changing the event
entirely or whatever. It's also because
the default configuration of like for
example the the meta SDK or basically
you can put the meta SDK and tell meta
okay just map my event on your own and
you have like the install for example is
the hardest to debug because it's not an
event it's something that cames
prepackaged so when it doesn't work
you've got less levers to move but for
example the free tri the paid conversion
can be mapped something that happens
very often is that a direct purchase
without a free trial and a free trial
that converts to pay and a renewal would
all be mapped to purchase together. How
can you actually read anything when
you've got this mixed bags of event
which I sometimes use a mixed bag of
event for optimization but as long as I
understand what's what's actually
passing through and I'm going to want
all of those individually to make sure
like okay I've unbugged that they work
properly now I can start getting a
little bit smarter around what I'm
sending and the default configuration is
not as easy as it looks I think is one
of the case where making a little bit of
effort because it's not something you
have to work every other day like it's
something like you need to fix, but then
you can run on this for 6 12 months. You
can never forget about it for the reason
I mentioned at the beginning. But uh
it's something that you fix once in a
while and also because it gives you
options like I was working with an
account where they had like massive
success scaling on couple different
platforms like really impressive
trajectory went from zero to eight
digits in a couple years like a very
beautiful trajectory. And then at some
points things started working not as
well and we tried everything we could
like you know creative and fixing the
event and so on. One of the problem is
that they put all their eggs in one
basket and that basket worked great for
a long time but when it broke they had
no alternative. And one of the reason to
have your your signals properly handed
is also to have optionality in the sense
of if what works the best for you is
optimizing for free so be it. Or
optimizing for value like for revenue
optimization so be it. that's great,
double down on it and spend 90% on
there, but you probably also want to
have the other options available
sometimes because it's audience
expansion. And I would run an event
optimization campaign towards free trial
in parallel of a revenue optimization
campaign and Facebook would bring
different users to the app. So for
scaling, but also for the many many case
where things starts to break, which is
much more often than people think. So
I'd rather have different options in my
in my toolbox basically. maybe not for
today if something works like sure let's
let's go all in on it but to have this
for for later also to prep to experiment
a little bit on the site so yeah uh so
one of the reason I started talking
about it about this topic was one I had
the case I had two cases in in my
portfolio where one clearly had their
events broken so we needed to fix it and
then we thought if we're going to fix it
let's fix it and make it smarter at the
same time and then I had another client
who who work with a third party. They're
already doing some kind of optimization
on their own and actually already a
fairly sophisticated system. I thought,
what if there's something I missed?
Let's go and ask some of the best out
there about what they're doing and we
actually handed it over to them. We're
running two tests. One is looking good,
the other one not. So, it's not
completely uh let's say conclusive, but
uh they definitely did stuff that we
wouldn't have done on our own and and go
one step beyond. So these two things
about fixing getting smarter and going
on stium they all came at a moment where
at the same time I felt that 95% of the
debate on paid media was about creative
production. I was like sure should be
talked but that's not the only topic. So
I like to take my contra hat and say I'm
going to talk about something else.
Suddenly I also noticed a lot more talks
about that. So uh either really good
timing or just people got inspired and
worked on it. I think it was a little
bit of both, but uh I'm I'm happy the
topic has picked up a little bit. It
doesn't mean that if you've got amazing
signal engineering and you have one ad
in your account, it's going to work.
That's not that's not going to work.
Like
>> Yeah. Um before we move on to to like
more specifics around how to do the
signal engineering, I did want to ask
one more question on the data again,
just because I these are kind of
questions I think people would be, you
know, shouting into their car as they're
driving around listening to the podcast.
is that h how do you think about this
when you're scaling on multiple
networks? So you're you're doing Google
and Meta and Tik Tok. Should each of
those events managers be seeing 100% of
your conversions, 100% of your free
trials, 100% of everything? Is that what
you're looking for in each individual
event manager? or are you looking for
Google to be seeing just a percentage of
the events and and Meta to see be seeing
a percentage of the events?
>> If you're early in this process, you
probably want them all to receive 100%.
Like you don't filter anything. You send
100% of these different events. Uh yes,
it's almost normal that the same signal
is not going to be the best for every
platform and it's possible that you end
up optimizing for revenue in meta and
for a qualified trial in Google and for
a filter of direct purchase and trial
conversion in Tik Tok to say something
like what's going to work is not not
going to be universal like every network
have different type of user but also
different context but also different
ways of optimizing like of of valuing
the signal. that you send them and on
top of it they don't have the same
source. You might be using an MMP and
send to all these sources but it's also
very possible that you're sending to
Google via Firebase and to Facebook via
the Facebook SDK and so on. So like the
easy answer is yes send 100% of the
events to all the different platform in
reality one they're going to be
different source so they're different by
nature and different things are going to
work. So, for example, you might have to
filter younger audience trials to Tik
Tok, but you don't necessarily need to
do it for meta because it works
differently. Like what I do is I map
these different events. So, let's say
I've got my free trials. I send them
all, but maybe I'm never using them in
any campaign. And then, so I can verify
the quality of the data that's being
passed. And then I've got my qualified
free trials or filtered free trials,
let's say, being sent to the different
networks. But I map it. When I say map
is like I declare it as a different
event. So maybe all the free trials are
going to be called start trial but then
the qualified trial is going to be
called whatever it's going to be maybe a
purchase maybe subscribe maybe something
actually I I wish that the platform
offer us more options in in the number
of events that they propose because
probably because it's not so common
that's why the list is is limited and if
we remember two or three years ago
Facebook didn't even have start trial
subscription it was all purchase from
gaming and ecom. So the baseline then is
that as you start to think about signal
engineering, the first step is that 100%
of your data is going to all the
different networks and you just verify
that you're within that like 5 to 10%
threshold across all the different
networks. Then you move on to starting
to filter the events and then by doing
so then you have a better sense for what
numbers should be showing up on each
platform because then you can determine
I'm not sending free trials of users
under 25 to Tik Tok and so you can do
the math then of like okay we know that
when I was sending 100% it was working
and so now I'm only sending you know 75%
and so now I have an idea of like what
should be arriving at that particular ad
network and then that's how you do your
data validation once you start doing the
signal engineering right
>> yeah correct I mean all of this well I
remember doing this in 2017 and and it
didn't come up from a brilliant idea in
my mind it just come up from the
observation that my free trial rates on
Google ads was terrible like we would
have like let's say 40% trial to paid
conversion on organic on meta like I
mean small differences and then we'd
have like 15% on Google it was like what
what are we doing wrong here and like
okay for Google we're going to identify
the some of the reason those trials are
not converting and we're going to send
them a different signal to try to fix
it. It was not like we're not trying to
be smart and just do senior engineeric
but we started from a problem initially
like maybe if you don't have this
problem of maybe if your free trial
quality coming from from paid is great
you don't need to go further for now
like maybe you you could do even better
but like I started from a from a problem
and then seeing that this was moving the
needle in ways I said okay now I can get
a little bit smarter one of the next
step is that historically all these
platforms so They they offer event
optimization. So they offer instant
optimization which honestly you should
never do. There are a couple edge cases
where you might but in most cases a very
bad idea. There's event optimization
which can be different event. They can
be filtered and so on. And we can talk a
little bit more. And there's revenue
optimization. And the problem with
revenue optimization is that from the
gaming world and e-commerce world this
was just revenue. This was just revenue
that was generated by the sale. But in
subscription, because we've got the the
free trial and because we've got the
renewals, the revenue that is actually
happening that day is actually not what
we need to send back to the platform. So
I started getting smarter and say,
"Okay, I'm going to engineer the revenue
that I'm sending." So it's not a
predicted LTV is a predicted value at
day x. Maybe it's months two. Maybe it's
personally I like to use months 13
because I've got the first yearly
renewal and I think it's a better
comparison between monthly and yearly.
But whatever, it doesn't matter what I
like. The real revenue, the one that
passed by default on the SDK is not the
one that I want to be sending because
the free trial conversion is going to
come too late because it's going to
overvalue the yearly over the monthly.
But maybe or or let's take the weekly.
Sometimes the weekly the LTV of a weekly
is great because the price is so much
higher. If somebody renews for six
months on the weekly plan, the revenue
where we want to send to the platform is
not the real one. uh it's going to
typically platform are going to
overindex on yearly because all the
revenue comes on day one but maybe your
weekly plan has a higher LTV when people
run you alone. So you're just telling
the platform something that is wrong
about what you're looking for. And here
the idea is not only to trick and I I
remember talking to Andre about senior
engineering and and and they summarize
it that oh Thomas is manipulating the ad
platform. I'm like no I'm manipulating
data to send the platform what is the
closest value of the users they're
sending me. I'm not trying to lie here.
At the contrary, I'm trying to fix
something that is broken in the sense of
the platform is receiving a value that
is not representative of my business
value. Like the default configuration is
not what representative one thing I'm
working on right now for example is that
users that are not converting within 24
hours but are demonstrating a very high
likelihood of retaining for long as a
premium user or converting later. We're
going to assign a small value to it. So
not the 10 per month or 90 per year or
whatever but maybe $1 like because I'm
like I like this user and if I send zero
there's zero event there's zero value
the platform is going to conclude that
this is the kind of users I don't want
and maybe because they create the
network effect they create dau they
create late conversions that are very
hard for the network to assimilate I'm
going to have to send something that
shows them hey this user is really zero
but that one is actually a little
something the whole scheme there is I
want to tell Meta, I want to tell
Google, I want to tell Tik Tok about
what's valuable for me because it's not
natural for them. They just received a
very primitive signal. I heard from Meta
last week that they were working on
optimizing towards different event at
the same times like for example
different tiers of subscription and
stuff and I was very happy because it's
something that I always wanted to do and
that you can almost only do by
engineering the signal and engineering
the the revenue behind it. Uh so so
we're getting there. It's just I want to
send something that is representative of
value so that the platform can do the
work they do the best way they can. And
they're really really strong at
predicting which users are going to
complete the action that I'm telling
them. But if the action I'm telling them
is wrong, you're running on one leg
literally. And that's where the whole
idea of signal engineering and
optimization of the data that you're
sending back comes from. It's like,
yeah, send the network something better
and they're going to do a better job
because they are doing a better job.
It's you who are not doing yours.
>> Nice. So, you've you've kind of gone
into and given a lot of what I would
guess were are kind of more advanced
signal engineering practices, but let's
step back and like once you get your
data right or believe you have your data
right, what's the lowhanging fruit in
signal engineering?
Where would you say are the first kind
of few steps folks should take to start
changing the default mappings of how
these SDKs operate by default? Like
what's the first step? So we mentioned
that's what's the second step because
the first step is is monitoring that the
events are passive properly which is not
a given but the second step for me would
be either going to what we call
qualified trials or filter trials and
typically that would be when you see
that your free trial rates are either
not as good as other networks or not as
good as what they used to be and also
because you don't need huge engineering
around revenue prediction and so on to
do this Like so basically make a
regression of okay let's analyze this
free trial that are not converting
sometimes is a combination of like what
I call hard factors which are like the
device itself maybe the language like
not something the user has told me but
something that is like in the hardware
itself it's well known that the most
recent device converts much better and
so maybe I'm going to filter all this
very old iPhone actually it's funny when
you look at the the specific device the
very latest device on on Android the
Google Pixel and the the latest Samsung
Galaxy and a couple of others, they
convert just as well as an iPhone. Those
like they only represent 5 to 10% of the
market and the rest have a terrible
conversion rate, but I certainly so so
you could like try to weigh in those and
Facebook has been working on the signal
engineering because there's very few
other levers that we can do, but
Facebook has finally put out of beta one
that we used to call it bit modifier for
a very very long time. And I could tell
Facebook, oh, when you're seeing one of
those Google pixel straight assign 20%
plus than any other users because I know
they're going to convert easier, they're
going to renew longer and so on. But
when you're seeing one of those old
Android
7 or whatever, don't even show them the
ad. But then very often your choice is
binary. Like let's take the age because
in subscription age is a very common
factor for people entering a free trial
and not converting. for a very long time
the solution was okay let's stop
advertising to people below 25 and then
I don't have the this problem anymore I
was like but I'm actually missing out on
something is that there's a lot of
inventory part of what I'm doing I mean
my app fits 15 to 25 years old it's just
that I have this free trial issue that
is going there I just want to factor it
I just want to I don't want to exclude
everybody below 25 because I'm I'm
limiting my options and so this is just
another way to do it differently so so
Somebody asked me recently, "Oh, but now
that I have the bid modifier, I can tell
Facebook that the sub 25 are 30% less
valuable. I don't need to do all these
filtering of trials and like I'd prefer
to hammer from both sides personally,
but sure, like it's it's kind of a
potential replacement, but it's not
available everywhere. The low angle is
probably going to be on qualified trials
because it's such a common factor,
>> but it doesn't mean it's for everybody."
And what is the hard factor? And the
other one is soft factor. And the sub
factor is something the user does. The
most common is a question at the
onboarding that somebody answers and
that filters maybe they declare this
interest and not this one. Like I have a
mental health app where when people say
they have a high level of anxiety there
so much more valuable than when they say
something else. And so we we factor this
question. The next level the very
sophisticated level would be to actually
add questions at the on boarding that
creates this variance. And that's what
you're looking for. So the the
lowhanging fruit is looking at in a
regression of the value based on
questions like this. And in revenue for
example, I was working on with somebody
was like super committed. Yeah, I need I
need to do something very sophisticated
with my revenue. Send to the ad
platform. I've got a whole team of
expert data analysts and engineers that
we can put some predictive LTV back to
Facebook and so on. Yeah. Let's look at
your revenue. Actually, you've got zero
violence. like you've got a binary case
where almost everybody ends up
generating this in the same range of
value. In this case, they no need to
overkill it. But if you notice that
you've got extreme variance, then it's
probably a case of jumping the qualified
trial and go straight at making these
revenue buckets because you've got a
bunch of users that are going to consume
$1A. You've got a bunch of users that
are going to take the $20 subscription
per month. And then you've got the pro
user with the $200 clone subscription. I
don't even know what it's worthy
subscription. And then if you've got
extreme variance in revenue, I think the
lowhanging fruit is to deploy the
resources needed because the qualified
trial are not going to be enough. Like
it's just like step one. So it depends
the problem you have like or the
problems you don't have. If you don't
have variance, don't bother with it. If
you don't have a free trial conversion
problem, don't bother filtering your
trials. Let's dig into exactly how you
do this. So, I I liked your example. If
you're a mental health app and you have
an onboarding question that says, "What
are your goals in using this mental
health app?" And one of the goals is
calm my anxiety. Another goal is just
like, "I just want to be healthier." You
know, some like really broad generic
goal. And so, you see the people with
that broad generic goal, you know, their
value is just way lower. And the ones
who you know have a specific problem to
solve like anxiety their value is way
higher. How do you actually instrument
this? Is this inside the app that when
you map the events you're not actually
sending the events and you're and and do
you have to prevent the SDKs from just
hoovering up all the events so that you
can send the specific event that you
want to send? Like how do you actually
do this?
>> Sure. I'll answer you but I'll make a a
cautious word before which is filtering
out like excluding people can work and
I've done it a number of times but is a
little bit my last resort like if I can
find another way to not fully exclude
these people because they might generate
less value less is not zero so excluding
them is actually something that I try to
avoid in the first place and when I look
let's say an on boarding question and
I'm going to have okay high anxiety I
want to be healthier or I just want to
sleep better and I'm going to Look, if
something is extremely less value, in
which case I'm going to try to exclude
it. If it's a little bit less value, I'm
going to try to find something else.
Either I'm going to let it pass and deal
with it. I'm going to move to revenue
optimization or I'm going to try to find
if it correlates with a particular
demographic to use the bit modifiers or
I'm going to try something else. Like
the exclusion is kind of if I can't do
any other way, then I'm going to
exclude. Let's say I need to filter out
some people. Basically some people in
the in the onboarding they're just
telling you oh I'm just browsing around
I don't know really the intent like this
basically what I'm tell they're telling
you and those I'm probably going to want
to exclude in this case either you've
got the platform SDK so like or
typically you're sending it through an
MMP more rarely through like a custom
API the custom API you send whatever you
want so like I mean you filter the event
yourself you send it but it's the least
common case through the MP what I'm
doing is actually asking my engineers.
I'm going to want to add a new event.
I'm not going to filter the existing
event. The free trial is going to remain
a free trial. Okay. If there is a free
trial and the answer to this question is
this, then send it to adjust apps or
singular as being subscribe or whatever
and then Facebook is going to start
receive it and I'm going to have it. It
works the same in the Facebook SDK like
you just can have the default
configuration but then you can set up
your own events. And I'm not talking
about custom events. just you can force
but that's done on the engineering side
that's something the marketers are not
doing that's something that requires to
open the code and actually do it so I
know marketers are getting smarter with
code these days but and this is one
thing where I called it signal
engineering because there's engineering
behind it in the sense of I'm actually
tweaking the system a little bit but
also because very often you do need an
engineer it's an interesting dynamic how
very few developers are actually
interested in all things marketing
there's always a little bit of of
attention in this ticket because we
marketers are terrible to explain our
requests and to like properly define the
requirements and so it comes into back
and forth but also I don't know a lot of
engineers who love the tweaking the
Facebook SDK SDK that's very rare like
something I got a few buddies now that I
can rely on but uh it took many years to
get to this point and it's actually very
easy to execute but the fact that the
marketer who's requesting it and the
developer who's actually making the
change are not speaking the same
language at all. It look very
complicated and even now I'm surprised
sometimes in a couple of this
conversation where I'm just answering oh
I no idea how you do that but I know
it's possible here in the documentation
it says it's you can do it here I've
described what I want that's your job to
deal with it not mine and and it always
gets down but like my technical
knowledge gets to a limit pretty fast
when it gets there but I mean with a
with an MPS SDK is not very complicated
either I mean once you figure it out
once
>> it can get more complicated later like
for example for value for the value
optimization. One thing that happened is
that
it doesn't go through an SDK but through
an API that sends back the information
to the SDK. I'm like okay so I've got
this combination of we could hardcode
it. We could say okay if there is a this
plan that is done on this device having
answered this particular question at on
boarding then the value is 56 and if
it's the other combination it's 23 and
we could hardcode this but then every
time I need to update and that happens
constantly because we change plan
currency value change and so on I would
need to have the code touch and then
another release. So if I know I'm going
to do a lot of signal engineering later,
what I'm doing is actually there's an
API call and say, okay, I've got all
these parameter, what's the value right
now? Oh, 56 and next week there's going
to be 68. And I'm not going to have
anyone touch the code anywhere, but I
can dynamically change it. And one
particular case where you do want it
like this is when you operate in
countries where the currency tend to
fluctuates a lot. Turkey is a very big
one. For example, Turkey where yeah, if
you hardcode the value there, you're
dead. But that's kind of sophisticated
and it can break because then you've got
the SDK talking to an API like it's not
necessarily where you want to start. But
eventually uh it does make a big
difference. It's a great insight too
that uh as marketers it's something to
be cognizant of and to work toward is
better understanding at the code level
what's actually going on so that you can
work more collaboratively with the
engineering team to successfully deploy
these things and then to kind of
understand what's going on under the
hood to be able to troubleshoot when
it's not working well. And to your
point, the best implementation is one
that that is way more flexible and not
hard-coded versus like writing a bunch
of hard-coded stuff into the app that
every time you want to make any little
change, you're having to go talk to the
engineering team to make those changes
and then when something breaks, you got
to push an app update. And so, are there
any kind of specifics around building
that out that you've seen work really
well? like are there with certain
clients that you work with do you have
kind of tooling in place that's making
this a lot easier? When I ask the
developers they tell me no but dude this
is a very simple API is like there is
one call I reply the value it looks it
looks once they done it they're like oh
what you asked was actually super simple
why did we take 3 months to get there
because your explanation was wrong so it
was also my problem you know it was
basically a communication problem I
haven't used many tools around this
mostly internal tools and then you have
to adjust depending on if you're sending
to the platform SDK like firebase or
meta or via an MMP or via uh even like
cat and so on. So you have to adjust but
the rest was mostly internal. I'm
working now with a company called
Voyantis who does this filtering on
their own and then send it back
themselves. So I discovered a few new
tricks. There are very few people who
are working on this. I haven't heard
particularly of tools that sometimes you
might use a tool that's made for
something else in in the middle. But
technologically it's actually fairly
simple. It's just it doesn't always
work. There's always a little bit of
debate. But uh but in terms of code is
actually something that is that very
complicated. For me the most interesting
part is not so much the execution which
is I mean there are issues is regular
but there's nothing as a breakthrough
there. It's not like it's not that you
code it better that the signal is going
to be better is really how do you define
the signal that is going to make it and
all these questions around on boarding
and about segmenting users creating
buckets of value is actually really
interesting because it has a crossing of
like I mean there's a lot of data
analysis but there's always new stuff we
discover like there's so many factors
and I like to play around it across
different apps and I'll tell you one for
example like we noticed with somebody I
was working that The completion time of
the on boarding was a decisive factor in
end value and we were like okay those
people who are answering it in less than
a minute and there was like 30 screen
there was nothing like yeah probably
they click next next x next next they
start the free trial and they console
and I start bringing this to other apps
and they're like dude I checked and
actually my fastest body completion are
actually my best users because they
already know what they want and so on.
It's not universal necessarily and this
criteria is not a great one but there
are a couple that are usually very big.
So age we mentioned the thing around
goals is is very often a very big one
and a lot of apps have different types
of users. They would have like more pure
consumer users like full B2C but then
they would have small teams a lot of
solopreneurs people with a Shopify shop
or influencers who are actually they're
one person business like and there's a
lot of them if you manage to identify
who are like these small business one
person business solopreneurs they
typically have a completely different
bit of course if you're improving their
business because the post gets seen more
or the video higher quality or whatever
Yeah, the the price sensitivity of this
because it's their business is obviously
very different from somebody who's just
trying to make their photo look better.
And this is one that is one of the most
common things like so yeah, age goals
and I don't know how to define this like
typology of users between like consumer
and proumer and real businesses like and
big businesses like uh uh this one is a
very big one. Yeah, I know you talk to
the MMPs a lot and have some limited
insights into some of these ad networks.
Is this something you think the MMPs and
ad networks could do better? Like
should, you know, Appsflower and Adjust
and Singular, you know, should they be
building these kind of signal
engineering tools into their tooling to
to make this easier? And then you
already mentioned that like the bid
multiplier and things like that that
Meadow is doing. Do you think these
kinds of things are going to get easier
and easier over time as the value is
recognized and then both the MMPs and
the ad networks are going to make this
kind of stuff easier? And then just to
complicate the question a little bit
more, how much of this will ultimately
start to get solved with meta
specifically, but all the other, you
know, major app networks are using more
and more AI to figure and machine
learning. really it's machine learning
they've been doing a long time but uh
we'll just call it AI. How much of this
is just going to get better and better
by default as the platforms are able to
figure these things out with better
machine learning and more sophisticated
tooling on their end.
>> So there's more or less three question
I'm going to answer in in a different
order that they came in. as of the ad
platform offering more options to like
put a weight on each value like the bit
modifier on Facebook which is now called
value based rules even though those two
things are not the same but doesn't
matter
>> I think we're not going to see a lot of
it it's not the direction it's taking
the direction it's taking is hands off
marketers let us do it we're doing it
better than you will ever know like
>> which I tend to disagree with not that I
wanted all manual like it was 10 years
ago all the machine learning that has
been deployed toward world conversion
optimization by meta in Google has been
insanely successful and we don't want
this back. We would be much worse off
without it and you can see it that it's
where the smaller platform have a
problem because the amount of effort to
deploy this cost the same to a smaller
platform to to a big platform but the
reward is not the same. So smaller
platform tend to be a lot more primitive
and it plays against them and that ends
up that we marketers end up
concentrating all our money on the same
baskets because those baskets are much
more efficient and they don't want to
give us more control. So Facebook
actually does it a little bit but all
the others and the direction it's taking
is actually less of it. So I'm not
expecting to see more of it and that's
why I need to do it more on my side
because the platform gives me less and
less levers to pull. So I'm going to
play on a lever that I mean they can't
prevent me from deciding what I'm
sending them and they do want this
signal anyway. So this is where it's
still going to get deployed. So that was
one question. Two, could the MMP help
there? I think they could. They could by
making it a little bit easier also
because they see patterns like there are
only a few MMPs and they have a very
large number of clients. So they do see
patterns and they could communicate not
of oh play is doing this and Tinder is
doing that but more like oh in this
vertical it's very common to filter or
in this vertical be very careful about
how you send your ads revenue or
whatever and so one on the educational
side and I don't think it's been dealt
so much and two in actually making it
more default the problem here is that
everybody's has their own and typically
on boarding question is not something
that you can have defa default in any
SDK it's going to be the the actual
developer who needs to declare okay I've
got this question is never going to be
the same across across two apps so it's
kind of hard for them to deploy at scale
I think it it should be part of the
educational package and like oh you can
do this this this I think they haven't
done it much because it's so unique to
every app but also because in their
place it's kind of like yeah as soon as
you send us an event we're going to send
it to the platform that's my job like
and we're already doing it. As soon as
you send it to me, I'm I'm going to
process it nicely, but maybe they could
do a little bit more. And and the last
question was,
is AI going to replace this on the
platform side? And in part, yes, and
it's already what they're doing, but
they've done as much as they could, and
they've gone very, very far. The last
piece in my opinion is on our side
because it's so unique and because I
don't want the platform to deal with my
data the exact same way that they deal
with the average of my sector. I want it
to be the closest possible to my and
sometimes even my own internal goal they
change over time. I'll tell you one
example. I have one particular case
where we used to optimize towards a
predicted LTV and then suddenly we
realized that cash flow was more
important and we realized that it was
not the same user who bring the maximum
LTV C or return after 5 years than the
one who bring it after 3 months and
we're like okay right now it's more
important that we maximize short-term
payback
okay let's change it you know and this
is not something the platform is going
to decide for me like I have to decide
this for myself but also because every
configuration is a little bit unique
that's said I believe there will be AI
and machine learning but not on the
platform side to decide on my side that
could come from amplitude of mix panel
that could come from revenue who says
look we've got access to all your
subscribers and we've detected that
there's 20% of those that are very low
value 20% of those are extremely high
value and we're going to package it into
here are three events if you want to use
them use them if you don't want to use
them use them so here. I don't think
it's going to be Facebook and Meta who's
going to do the job or Apploving or
whoever. It's a little bit hard for the
MMPs. It could be, but I think it's more
going to come from products and
subscription data tools like gravity
cut. So, actually, it's more of a
request. It would be very nice to have.
I'm not uh but I think you're in a
better place to do it than MMPs,
>> right?
>> The data you have around revenue is much
more solid.
>> Yeah. That makes a ton of sense.
>> It came back to you fast here, huh?
Yeah.
So, I did want to get into the more
advanced side of things. So, so we've
kind of stepped through this, you know,
step one, make sure your data is good.
Step two, you know, pick off some of the
lowhanging fruit. And then you said, you
know, step three is to really dive deep
and do some of these more advanced
stuff. and you've sprinkled in a lot of
the more advanced stuff along the way,
but I wanted to give you an opportunity
to like really nerd out and like go deep
onto like what these more kind of
advanced signal engineering processes
look like.
>> In my opinion, as soon as you get a
little bit sophisticated, you it's going
to be done at revenue level. Like you're
going to share tweaked revenue, filtered
revenue. It's never going to be filtered
events. The problem of events is that
they happen. It's binary. Either they
happen or they don't happen. and the
platform they can only optimize toward
one event, not two or three. I mean, you
can add them up, but it's they're going
to have the same value to the platform,
which may change in the future. And I
hope Meta is going to release this and
then eventually Google, but uh we're not
there yet. The most sophisticated stuff
is done at the revenue level because I
can be so much more granular about this
users $1, this user is worth 10. That
say uh I'll do my own devils advocate
against my opinion like some advanced
stuff can be done at the event level and
I know voyantist for example believes
that the timing of which you send the
event is actually creating a difference
and they proved it against what I betted
so they won on that one. I'm still not
very good at engineering it myself but
they showed me that it's true actually
sending it early or later could make a
difference. Not too late either, but
like sometimes you got a free trial
happening, but even the on boarding
question and the other criteria we
talked to, they're not good enough to
decide if this free trial is like highly
likelihood to convert or low likelihood
to convert. You could preferably prevent
the event from being fired, wait from
for one or two hours, notice that oh
these users, this group of users have
done three activities, three meditation,
three workout, three whatever within two
hours and this group has not and I'm
only going to fire those ones and not
the others. So you could delay a little
bit the event still work on event and do
it. Personally, I think all the
sophisticated stuff happen at the
revenue level because you can be so much
more precise about how you send it. My
other argument against the the timing is
that and I'm going to join the
sophisticated question back into the
lowhanging fruit is that I'm entirely
convinced that whatever comes after 24
hours is useless for the platform to
optimize towards which is a very hard
ask because a lot of apps especially in
gaming need a full week of seeing how
users come back to the app, what they
do, do they cover later, do they
actually start with a small purchase
before going up? Yeah, it would be great
if or or with free trial is the same
case because then you've got 3 days. I
had the question recently like somebody
was like, "Oh, if I reduce my free trial
from 7 days to 3 days, it's going to be
much easier for the platform to see this
data after the third day." I was like,
"No." Anyway, if it's not the first day,
in my opinion, it's not entirely
useless. It's not 100% useless, but in
my opinion, you need to find something
that happens on the first day. And that
makes that you might prevent the the the
event from being shot in the moment it
happens, but you want to send it in the
first hours. You wait a few hours and
then you send it and then that's it.
That's what you got. So one of the
lowhanging fruit here is don't optimize
for your 7 day or 14 day whatever uh is
optimize something for for day one. And
the advance stuff is move it to revenue
so you can tweak it further and further
and further and then you're going to
edit on the goal and it's going to be
and you add a new plan and you can
easily add okay I've got a new type of
plan or I've got a promo and I'm going
to edit the value very close to what I
think acts and that can include also
like for example you could detect that
refund have a particular pattern that
some people who are more likely to
refund they've done this and this and
that and then users who've done this and
this and that you would assign a
slightly different value. You're never
sure. I mean, it's all probabilistic.
It's not like at user level, yes, a user
converses trial or refunds or renew, but
then in campaigns, you're going to have
a bag of these users and you're trying
to get as close as reality as you can
get. And one thing that is actually hard
like is I've got this with a team right
there where we're monitoring the value
we're sending the platforms against the
real value that's happening. And we've
got like this curve that are following.
And as soon as we see that there's a gap
in there like we know something is going
wrong. As dynamic and sophisticated as
the model is, it never follows the exact
reality. So we're looking at closing the
gap always and always. This developer
works on being as close as possible as
the real value. But then you can
engineer further and I had this other
conversation with you can fake it. And
typically something that I do is I like
to amplify it to make the network's job
even easier. So, let's say, let's
simplify the situation. I've got users
worth $5 and I've got users worth $50.
Well, what I'm going to tell the
platform is that this $5 are actually
three, but that this $50 is actually
100. Like, and I'm going to force it
like I'm going to make it a little bit
more extreme. The trick here is that it
makes that I can't really read the value
anymore in the platform. I can't read my
rowass on Facebook because it's all
fake. I'm going to look at it on my
side, but it's okay. I'm going to try to
force the platform to gear toward the
users that are most valuable to me by
forcing it a little bit. And this fun
conversation with someone from gaming
who said, "Oh, I do the opposite." What?
So, when you have a high value user, you
take the platform that is a medium value
user, say, "Yes, because we've got
whales." And then if I really declare a
big whale of 500 or a,000, Meta is going
to say, "That's it. My job is done for
the day. I bring that one user and I'm
done." So, they actually cap it. The
thing is that it it's a lot more rare in
subscription that you want to do that.
But let's say you've got this tier of
subscription with Chat GPT. Maybe Chad
GP is going to fake it that the $200
plan is actually only 100
>> because otherwise the campaign could
derail faster if too many of these user
come simultaneously. So you want because
at the end of the day the the machine of
optimization they're very sophisticated
but they're also a little bit dumb and
sometimes when you when they see a
couple good signals coming they start
like completely changing delivery and
yeah we're playing with fire a little
bit here because one we experiment on
the way and I made a few mistake on the
way and but two it can derail pretty
fast in a way that you haven't predicted
and which if you look at it from the
network side from app login or from
Facebook and you look at it and
Uh yeah, it's kind of logical that if
they saw all this revenue happen that
day, the next day they delivered in a
way that basically it went too fast and
too extreme. So you need to find a
balance because me often I make it more
extreme than it is but there is a limit
to this like you can't go too far with
this like don't don't don't push it. I
also had a very interesting conversation
with somebody else who was like, is it
better to fake it that you're making
more revenue so that Facebook will think
you're super successful and serve you
more than other advertiser
or will that actually come to eat your
margin and say, "Oh, this guy is making
too much money, so I'm going to underdel
it." I don't have the answer to this
question, but it's kind of an
interesting one to think about like how
much the platform itself is reacting to
the change we're making on that side.
>> Yeah. Uh it's also fascinating. So in
this advanced scenario, we're actually
manipulating the revenue
that you're sending back for the revenue
optimization goals. How does that
actually play out? So you're looking in
like amplitude mix panel or internal
dashboards and you're you're determining
back to our uh meditation app example
that you know somebody who answers
anxiety and does these other three
actions is our super high value user. So
you're kind of backtracking from known
data and the signals that you're seeing
inside the app and then assigning a
value to that. And then to your example
earlier as well is like you know if they
have this general need but they're still
monetizing but they're not not
monetizing great. Then you assign the $1
value. How are you doing that and how do
you think about that
>> before you go and take risk of of
changing the value itself to something
that you faked and you you think you're
smarter. I think I'm smarter and which
can backfire pretty fast. The logic of
it is just
making a regression of where where is
there variance like I know I've got
users of different values which are the
criteria that creates this variance. Is
it an on boarding question? Is it the
device? Is it the time code to
completion? Is it this? So it's
basically crossing this. Okay, I've got
this high value users and these low
value users and these zero value users.
What each do have in common that the
others don't? is basically a regression
is the reality is that many many times
I've explained the data analyst that I
want this job to be done and that his
goal is for him to find a criteria that
I didn't spot by myself like a new
criteria the reality is that the
criteria they're very often the same
they're the one we mentioned they're the
big one I guess as you go more
sophisticated and I had an interesting
talk with Ryantis about this again also
about the number of activities that
people do and when they do it and the
time of day And if they install on a
weekend and then it's a different
pattern like they go much further than
this but I think for most people like
basically looking at where does variance
comes like regression of which are the
criteria that create variance between
people who refund a lot between people
who renew a lot and usually you've got
95% of the job done like yeah if you
look for this where the variance is
coming like it should be good enough for
most cases.
>> Are any of the tools particularly good
at this? I know amplitude recently has
like this AI variance detection kind of
stuff. Are any of the tools especially
good at that? I wish the the problem is
that very often the the data is a little
bit scattered like amplitude would have
very very good but then the connection
with revenue cut or similar needs to be
extremely good as well like for the
revenue to be to be proper like very
often it comes from a variety of source
I think it's going to come but in the
case that I've seen myself it was done
manually from back end data like because
it's the only place where we had the
liberty to dig and query the data in
very very specific way ourselves
also because we could extract it and the
data the data list could run his own
model on it and not feel limited by what
the those models are offering but also
in one particular case because they had
very sophisticated internal tooling and
they do have amplitude and they do have
an MMP and so on but in their own back
end they've got the equivalent of
radicat and the equivalent of amplitude
for every single screen and so obviously
this case the data was more complete
there if somebody has a mixed panel
amplitude conction with render that is
really properly done and a very large
cohort of users eventually it's going to
be it's going to be done automatically
maybe there's a joint work to be done
here between you and them but most of
the ones I've seen they were manual and
I think the reason is that one is a
little bit of a pirining field still two
there's a lot of predict this stuff so
it's very unique and three yeah very
often you would engage different source
of data together and even though you
have cut there and even though for
example in amplitude I can plug also the
MMP data so I can filter by source it's
not something that is supernatural it's
not something that is like completely
well done out of the box because it's
made for product analytic people it's
not for product managers and not for
user acquisition specialist
>> yeah it's not a revenue optimization
tool it's a analytics tool
>> exactly it's not what it's made for and
it I don't think it's impossible and
some people will do it like this but uh
I I know I've I've struggled with some
limitation in some cases.
>> Yeah, that makes a lot of sense. Well,
we've we've gone quite long, but I I I
wanted to give you an opportunity for
kind of a grabag here at the end of
other considerations that we haven't
discussed. So, like, you know, one of
them that we talked about on the webinar
was the trade-offs you make in volume of
events versus quality of events. So why
don't you cover that first and then just
a grabag of anything else that you think
people should be considering as they
embark on their signal engineering
journey.
>> The volume versus quality. I mean we
didn't comment it today. So for whoever
has missed the previous webinar and not
read the article that I haven't posted
yet necessarily they've missed it. So
I'll go back to it because it's pretty
fundamental. But uh yeah, you can have a
fantastic event if the platform is
seeing one or two every day is not going
to work. Like the filtering I mentioned
before like for me filtering out people
is the last resort. But that's not true.
If I I've got a very large amount of
data, I would be more inclined to
exclude people and is the number of
events you said. So here is at campaign
level like every campaign basically
there's a threshold of optimization that
networks there's no exact number but the
the number that's floating around is
somewhere between 50 and 100 per week.
So I simplify in my head and say below
10 event per day per campaign things are
going to go a little bit wrong. It's a
bit the more the marrier. So if I can
have 25 instead of 10 I'd rather not
filter and I have 25. And if I have 40
instead of 20 then I have 40. It's
better. But once you get there, there's
very little upside to sending 300 every
day. And there's a lot of upside of
sending only 30 every day, but that are
super filtered. So in this case, this is
where the trade-off between volume and
quality is. So if you're too early,
basically, you can't do qualified trials
almost because you already only have
five trials per day. So don't try to
filter them like almost you'll want to
go higher up before the free trial. say
okay these users haven't tried a free
trial but they've shown very good intent
around around on boarding questions
about the first activity I'm going to
also send them so that I have more event
and so the more event you have the more
you can filter around that's pretty
clear and this trade-off is is pretty
fundamental that day on the webinar we
didn't talk too much about timing but I
think I covered it decently today also
covering the the other part the
prosecutive part but uh the timing is
important and my rule here is don't wait
don't wait too long you can wait a
little bit but don't wait too So timing
is one and the amount is one. The amount
is very critical. It's something because
over time maybe the best engineering you
can do today is very different from the
one you can do in six months. Just
because your budget has moved from 100K
to 500K enables you to do a very
different kind of filtering. Also
because your cohort has grown. So before
even with the teams that have the most
sophisticated model we keep revisiting
the the value that we're giving because
plans change because we make
monetization change because the mix of
of channel is different as well and the
whole user maybe because there's a
crisis maybe because there's this like
if you're based on an aggregation of
five years of data here is also a big
trade-off about how recent or how much
data do I have and like sort of I've got
this rule for example in in one case
which is if we've got enough users in
the last two weeks to make a decent
prediction we use this but if we don't
then we expand to three months and if we
don't then we're going to loosen up one
criteria a could be a could be a country
could be a number question and so on
because otherwise and I made this
mistake several times like you create
useless fluctuation on on very small
samples so obviously the more data you
have the easier it gets it's not a fixed
thing So the advice here the TLDDR is
revisit your assumption every now and
then every every 6 months or whatever or
at least control that gap between what
we're sending and what is actually
happening is not too big and the thing
about this gap is the trap is to look at
total like we only have a 2% deviation
I'm like yeah but there's 10% of people
who are responsible for 80% of this
deviation so this is the one so don't
look at this gap only in total do
monitor that it doesn't go sideways too
much and countries is a big one here
like country platform. Maybe not every
single critter is needed, but at least
monitoring the value of the events that
you filter are fairly reliable at
country level over time is is kind of a
good idea.
>> All right. Well, this has been a blast.
Uh so much great information. This is
why we got to do it annually. You're
constantly learning new things and then
you're so open to share. And then I get
asked all the time, "Hey, can you make
an intro to Thomas?" I'm like, "Thomas
is busy. He's going to be busy the rest
of his life.
>> I'm too busy researching new topics for
David for the next one.
>> Exactly.
Uh but this is why we'll have to do it
annually is that you're you have your
stable of great clients that you're
making learnings from and so you're
you're not hesitant to share like a lot
of people. And so I really appreciate
like you're always just digging in there
and sharing what's working. And so this
has been a a master class in uh figuring
this kind of stuff out. So thanks again.
And then a quick plug, Thomas is
actually going to be doing a hands-on
workshop at Appgrowth annual. So that's
going to be October 14th in New York
City 2025.
So if you want to go super hands-on with
Thomas on single engineering, sign up
for Appgrowth annual. The workshops will
not be livereamed specifically because
we want people to be able to like share
and and really open up and have real
conversations. if you're wanting to dig
deeper, you you got to be in person for
the uh signal engineering workshop at
Appgrowth annual. So, I'm looking
forward to seeing you in a couple months
and uh thank you so much again for the
conversation today.
>> Yeah, likewise. Looking forward to
seeing you in person and thanks thanks
again for inviting.
>> Thanks so much for listening. If you
have a minute, please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player. You can
also stop by chat.subclub.com
subclub.com to join our private
community.
[Music]